Guide to the New York State Crime Commission Records
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
New York State Crime Commission Records
1942-1953.
New York (State). Crime Commission.
3 boxes.
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079160
Biographical Note
Lithgow Osborne was a member of the Commission.
Scope and Content
Papers relating to the investigation of waterfront crime, 1952-1953. Also, public hearings at Canton, N.Y., July 18-20, 1951.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 4 series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Manuscripts
Series III: Research Papers & Documents
Series IV: Publications
Subjects
Lithgow, Osborne.; Canton (N.Y.)--Law and legislation.; New York (State)--Law and legislation.; Criminal investigation--New York (State); Waterfronts--New York (State); Crime--New York (State)
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least two business days hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
12/29/1953 M-53-12-29 Osborne, Lithgow Gift
- Series I: Correspondence
  - From [Ben] To Hon. Joseph M. Proskauer, cc Messrs. Harlan, Wilkinson, Osborne and Mulrooney, June 5, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From Eugene Goddard, Chairman of the State of New York Joint Legislative Committee to make a Study of Election Law and Related Statutes, to the State Crime Commission, September 15, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From [Ben] to Judge Proskauer, cc. Hon. Edward P. Mulrooney and Hon. Lithgow Osborne., September 17, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From Lithgow Osborne to Hon. Joseph N. Proskauer, included memorandum on a possible recommendation to the Governor and Legislature by the State Crime Commission aimed at decreasing the influence of organized crime on our political processes, November 20, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - From Elsie M. Kerr, secretary to Mr. Osborne, to Miss Lillian M. Murphy, administrator, Department of Marine and Aviation, New York, July 15, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - From Lithgow Osborne, to Hon. Joseph M. Proskauer, cc. Ben Matthew, September 22, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Manuscripts
  - Waterfront Public Hearing, testimony of: A.P. Guistra, December 18, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Waterfront Public Hearing, testimony of: C. Scannavino, December 18, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Waterfront Public Hearing, testimony of: J. Mangiameli, December 18, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Waterfront Public Hearing, testimony of: S. Camarda, December 18, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Waterfront Public Hearing, testimony of: H.S. Lipman, December 18, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Waterfront Public Hearing, testimony of: A.V. Camarda, December 18, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Waterfront Public Hearing, testimony of: M. Russo, December 19, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Handwritten notes from testimony (Includes thoughts of author, possible Lithgow Osborne, on physical characteristics of testifiers), 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Financial Questionnaire, [1952] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Supreme Court, Appelate Division Charles Haydon vs. Joseph M. Proskauer, Chairman, Ignatius M. Wilkinson, Vice-Chairman, Edward P. Mulrooney, Lithgow Osborne and Samuel P. Capen, as members constituting the New York State Crime Commission., April 7, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Digest of information on certain arrest records – Confidential, [1952] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Proposed paragraphs for insertion in Commission’s Report re: General legislation applicable to labor unions, [1952] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Waterfront report, for discussion of sections, [1952] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Interim report of evidence adduced by the State Crime Commission relating to Six Brooklyn Locals of the International Longshoremen’s Association, by Peter M. Brown, Robert J. Ensher and George Berlstein, marked secret and confidential, September 1952, (2 copies ) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - A report by the New York State Crime Commission to the Governor and Legislature of the State of New York (draft), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Recommendations relating to waterfront labor employed on piers or wharves, January 1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - First report of the New York State Crime Commission to the Governor, the Attorney General and the Legislature (drafts), with covering memo from B.A.M. to Lithgow Osborne, January 1953, (2 copies ) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Second Report to the Governor and the Legislature of the State of New York, second of a series of reports by the New York State Crime Commission, embodying observations and recommendations based upon investigations conducted by the Commission (drafts), January 1953, (2 copies ) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Proposed draft of section dealing with Luchese, February 6, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Memorandum of draft of proposed recommendations relating to the waterfront, February 24, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Revised draft of proposed recommendations and covering memo from Leslie H. Arps to Commissioner Lithgow Osborne, March 6, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Third report to the Governor and the Legislature of the State of New York (drafts) includes covering memo from B.A. Matthews to Lithgow Osborne, March 11, 1953, (2 copies ) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Third report to the Governor, the Attorney General and the Legislature of the State of New York (draft for comments) includes covering letter from Ben A. Matthews to Lithgow Osborne, April 3, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Crime Commission, copies of draft bills for third report Marked “Confidential”, June 1953 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Fourth Report of the New York State Crime Commission to the Governor, the Attorney General and the Legislature of the State of New York (draft), April 20, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - “The Invisible Men” Memorandum on the plan of the book and point of view of the Authors, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Series III: Research Papers & Documents
  - Officers of six Brooklyn ILA Locals before and after the 1940 investigation by the Kings County District Attorney’s Office,1952 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Chart showing associations of Edward J. McGrath, and toll calls made and received by subject, [1952?] (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Large poster – New York State Crime Commission Tabulation of minimum and formula amounts paid to public loaders, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Small poster - New York State Crime Commission Tabulation of minimum and formula amounts paid to public loaders, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Memorandum of patronage appointments sampling, Supreme Court, First Judicial District, 1946-1951 [1952?] (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - List of present male district leaders who have worked in courts, January 1952 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Income of Joseph A. Marcell (Loaders Collection Service) and payments to “solicitors” for the period Jan. 1, 1945-Dec. 31, 1951, [1952?] (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Alex di Brizzi, Income from positions and ILA Orgs and known gratuities received, [1952?] (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Commission drivers and chauffeurs union statement of receipts 1945-1952 and Analysis of receipts and deposits 1945-1949, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Monies distributed from partnerships of A. Costa Jr. & Son and Service Collection Co., to named partners 1946-1952, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Thomas W. Gleason, income, gratuities, cross examination, sulphur deal, [1952?] (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - India Wharf Loaders, ratio of machine rental income of total operating income 1944-1951, [1952?] (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - India Wharf Loaders, distributions to the Doyle Brothers, as profits or salaries 1944-1951, [1952?] (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - International Longshoremen’s Association, payments, statement of receipts and disbursements 1947-1952, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Salvatore Padula and Peter Costello, Sr., withdrawals 1946-1950, [1952?] (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Pittston Stevedoring Corp., known payments to ILA officials and delegates, [1952?] (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - George Sellenthin Inc., earnings of steady employees 1948-1951, [1952?] (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Tabulation of amounts paid to loaders for 1949, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Cargo losses on voyages leaving and entering Port of New York 1949-1950, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Loading of perishables, Pier 34, North River, condensed statement of Operations, 1949-1951, [1952?] (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Condensed operating statements, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Employment in any federal, state or local unit of government of present male district leaders, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Bill to amend the General Associations Law by adding thereto a new article entitled Article II, [1952?] (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Bill 1083, Act to amend civil rights law and report on bill/disapproved, March 1953 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Memo filed with Assembly Bill, introductory #9, print #9: bill establishing Waterfront Commission for New York Harbor, June 1953 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - An Act to enter into a compact with the state of New Jersey for the reduction of criminal and corrupt practices in the handling of waterborne freight within the port of New York district and the regularization of the employment of waterfront labor, September 1953 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - An Act relating to unfair waterfront practices, December 1953 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Series IV: Publications
  - New York City Anti-Crime Committee Annual Report, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - “First Report to the Governor, the Attorney General and the Legislature of the State of New York” authored by the New York State Crime Commission, January 23, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - “Statutory Plan recommended by the Port of New York Authority”, January 1953 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - News releases, State of New York, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - News release from Xavier Institute of Industrial Relations re: recommendations of Rev. John M. Corridan, submitted to New York State Crime Commission, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Ogdensburg Public Hearing No. 1 at Canton, New York, July 18, 19 and 20, 1951 Volumes 1, 2 and 3 (bound) (Box 3)